Register of the Firing Line (Television Program) broadcast records 80040.4089238
Hoover Institution Archives
- Episode Guide, 1966-1999
  - "Government and Public Confidence" Guests: Muskie, Edmund S., 1914-, 21 January 1974 (Item Program Number S0125, 319)
    Program details: Senator Muskie's Subcommittee on Intergovernmental Relations had just commissioned the Lou Harris organization to conduct a poll on Americans' knowledge of and confidence in their country's institutions. The results on both counts were, as WFB relates them, pretty depressing. The bulk of the hour is spent--sometimes heatedly--analyzing the poll and debating how close it comes to reality. WFB: "But I am asking about the causes of alienation, and both you and I agree that there is alienation, isn't there?" EM: "Well, it seems to me that since you and I are accepting the poll's measure of whether or not there is alienation, we ought to be interested in how the poll arrived at that conclusion." WFB: "That's a technical question." EM: "That is not technical. It's very substantive." WFB: "The fact of the matter is--" EM: "Independent of this poll I have no personal antennae that tell me--" WFB: "Don't you?""
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.366
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6300
  - "The British Crisis" Guests: Lejeune, Anthony.: Levin, Bernard., 12 February 1974 (Item Program Number S0126, 320)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 108: 27
    Transcript: Box/Folder 171: 13
    Program details: The "crisis" of the title refers to the Heath Government's confrontation with the coal miners' union, which was demanding a 33 per cent pay increase. Mr. Heath had called an election--an election that he would lose, setting the stage for Margaret Thatcher's ascendancy. This show offers a spirited and wide-ranging discussion, exploring the differences between American and British law on strikes in essential industries, the differences in the two countries' electoral systems, and the causes of inflation. WFB: "[What about] the rather unexpected move of Enoch Powell. How do you interpret his decision not to run again?" (See Firing Line s0127.) BL: "I think Tony ought to speak first on that one because he's an old--" WFB: "Powell watcher?" BL: "...Powellite from top to bottom, and I'm not." AL: "I'm not a Powellite from top to bottom." BL: "From side to side, then." AL: "I'm a Powellite from side to side, yes. Two things only I'd say about it. One, I think that Powell could not have run on a Heath election platform. It would have been totally inconsistent with everything he's said, and since intellectual honesty is his main banner--Bernard may not believe it, but it is his main banner--it would have been quite illogical for him to run on this platform."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.371
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00G7085EK
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6305
  - "Enoch Powell and the British Crisis" Guests: Powell, J. Enoch (John Enoch), 1912-1998., 13 February 1974 (Item Program Number S0127, 321)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 108: 28
    Program details: Mr. Powell had announced that he would not run for re-election-not because he feared the Conservatives would lose, but because (as Mr. Lejeune suggests above) "the impossibility which I saw in front of myself was that in 1974 I should present myself to the same constituency advocating on most of the important issues the opposite to the policies for which I had invited them to vote four years before." (In the event, Labour's margin of victory was so narrow that a new election was called in October of that year; Mr. Powell run for election from Northern Ireland on the Unionist Party ticket and won.) The conversation focuses specifically on wage and price controls, more generally on inflation and the march of socialism; and on subjects such as these the eccentric Mr. Powell seems not at all eccentric: "The politician should never say that a trend is inevitable. It's his business to see to it that a trend, if he doesn't agree with it, is not inevitable. But I would be prepared to admit that if you wanted to make a case for the inevitability of a trend towards socialism, a very strong point that you could take up would be the fact that a Conservative government which came in in 1970 with a radical market philosophy ... within two years was introducing legislation which not merely re-echoed the legislation of the socialist party but exceeded their delighted dreams."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.373
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6307
  - "Tax Reform" Guests: Surrey, Stanley S., 21 January 1974 (Item Program Number S0128, 322)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 108: 29
    Transcript: Box/Folder 171: 14
    Program details: A thoughtful discussion of the federal tax system between two men who have spent much of their professional lives studying it and who are able to explain it to people who have not done so. WFB: "It seems to me plain from your philosophy that you more or less start off on the assumption that what you're dealing with is the government's money, whereas I start off on the assumption that what you're dealing with is the individual's money or the corporation's money. So what you insist on calling tax subsidies, tax expenditures, I would simply view as a form of remission...." SS: "I don't agree ...with the way you characterized my general position ... I would put it this way. We have decided to have an income tax in this country.... The base of the tax, the thing we're going to tax, is an individual's income." WFB: "Yes." SS: "Now, having decided that, then any exclusion from our concept of income becomes a particular preference for that individual as compared with other individuals who are differently treated."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.367
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00TZ8GX7C
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6301
  - "Politics and Black Progress" Guests: Bond, Julian, 1940-: Lewis, John, 1940 Feb. 21-, 23 January 1974 (Item Program Number S0129, 323)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 108: 30
    Program details: A detail-filled exploration of changes in voting practices, principally in the two guests' native South, since the passage of the civil-rights acts. JL: "In Dallas County, Alabama, in 1965, for example, only 2.1 per cent of the black people of voting age were registered to vote. Today more than 67 per cent... are registered to vote. They have paved streets, they have a sewer system.... In Greene County, Alabama, in 1965,...less than 300 black people were registered to vote. Today black people control the county. They are working with white people and they're working together. You have a housing authority there. For the first time in the history of that county black people have decent housing." And Mr. Bond tells how he learned something about the tendency among politicians, black or white, to "overpromise": "My notion of the $2 minimum wage, for example, vanished rather quickly when I found myself in the legislature and saw what the temperament of the body was."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.368
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00ANCWNG4
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6302
  - "Ulster: 1974" Guests: Hume, John, 1937-, 12 February 1974 (Item Program Number S0130, 324)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 108: 31
    Transcript: Box/Folder 171: 15
    Program details: An unusually lucid discussion of a tangled situation. In reply to Mr. Buckley's question--"Now, if something can last between 1921 and 1968, why can't it last out the balance of the century?"--Mr. Hume gives a masterly account of the threads that came together in the late Sixties to produce the violence that led, in 1972, to Britain's suspending Stormont and assuming direct rule of Northern Ireland. Britain had recently restored a measure of home rule; one of the conditions was that the Catholic minority had to be represented in the executive branch, which was why the Catholic Mr. Hume had been named Minister of Commerce. JH: "Well, the fear is consistently expressed by the Protestant majority in the North, which is a Protestant minority in Ireland, that... by coming into a united country they would be subjected to what they call 'Rome rule.' That fear is consistently expressed. I don't personally believe that if all of the changes they ask for took place tomorrow that would advance their wish for Irish unity one iota."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.370
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6304
  - "Catholicism and Socialism in Ireland" Guests: Browne, Noel C., 12 February 1974 (Item Program Number S0131, 325)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 108: 32
    Program details: A crackling exchange between a committed Catholic conservative and a committed socialist who holds the Catholic Church responsible for most of Ireland's ills--ranging from differing rates of infant mortality between rich and poor to the violence of the Provisional IRA. WFB: "If your criticism was intended to be understood as being leveled exclusively at the Irish Catholic Church, how would you explain the following sentence from one of your articles?-- The only possible response by those oppressed by the Church has been and is social revolution, half a bloody century of it, of which the most recent is seen in once-Catholic Cuba.-- How did the Irish Church get into Cuba? ..." NB: "I think you're playing games, if I may say so, Mr. Buckley.... There are many forms of the Catholic Church, and I disagree with the obscurantist Catholic Church. If there is such a thing as a radical Catholic Church or a Catholic Church that accepts the socialist idea, I have no objection to that kind of Catholic Church."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.372
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6306
  - "The Question of South Africa" Guests: Vorster, B. J. (Balthazar Johannes), 1915-, 13 March 1974 (Item Program Number S0132, 329)
    Background File: Box/Folder 91: 9
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 108: 33
    Transcript: Box/Folder 171: 16
    Program details: This was the first appearance ever of Mr. Vorster on television, and Mr. Buckley doesn't start him off easy: "I should like to begin by asking the Prime Minister whether, as almost every account of his background in America and elsewhere notes, he was in fact during the war pro-Nazi." JV: "No. I can definitely say that it wasn't a question of being pro-Nazi. I was anti-British...." WFB: "So that in fact to deduce from that that you were pro-Nazi would be as incorrect as to deduce that we were pro-Communist because we were on the side of Stalin." JV: "Quite.... I was pro-Afrikaans." Then onto the present, with the Prime Minister impressively discussing his country's policies on press freedom, comparative standards of living in different parts of Africa, and whether you can have a successful multi-racial society. JV: "I take it what you do mean in fact--maybe you were too polite to say it--is that it is said we are in fact a police state." WFB:"It's certainly said. Certainly, yes." JV: "If that is the case, then it's the only police state that I know of where you must do your level best to keep people out; because as it happens at the moment, we have thousands and thousands of illegal black immigrants in this country and we can't get them out."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.374
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00ANCWNS2
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6308
  - "The Question of Rhodesia" Guests: Smith, Ian Douglas, 1919-, 15 March 1974 (Item Program Number S0133, 330)
    Background File: Box/Folder 92: 1
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 109: 1
    Program details: This was only the second appearance of Mr. Smith on television. Mr. Buckley begins by reminding us that "in 1965 Rhodesia had requested independence of Great Britain, and Britain had said no, on the grounds that Mr. Smith's government represented only 5 per cent of the population. Whereupon at 11:15 A.M. on November 11, 1965, the government issued a Unilateral Declaration of Independence, the UDI, the second such declaration by a former colony in Britain's history--the first being our very own, which was signed before the word 'unilateral' was invented." As of this taping, Rhodesia remained a pariah nation, beleaguered by external sanctions and internal terrorism. An informative discussion of the history of colonialism in Africa, the current state of Rhodesia's economy, and the scene in nearby countries such as Mozambique and Zambia. One sample, on the subject of introducing democracy: IS: "The American people basically have always lived under this system. Now, we're dealing with people who say, 'But we don't understand this thing that the white man has brought here. We live under the tribal system. We're quite happy, we're peaceful. Why don't you leave us alone?' What do you say to them? 'You can't be left alone and peaceful. Whether you like it or not, you must come in and play a part with us'? It's not an easy question." Technical note: This program is black and white.
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.375
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0064EGLE0
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6309
  - "The Republican Party and Mr. Nixon" Guests: Bush, George, 1924-, 3 May 1974 (Item Program Number S0134, 331)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 109: 2
    Transcript: Box/Folder 171: 17
    Program details: Mr. Bush was developing a reputation as the holder of thankless jobs in the Nixon Administration--first, Ambassador to the United Nations at the time of the vote to eject Taiwan; now Chairman of the RNC during Watergate. His current task was to help as many Republicans as possible get elected to Congress six months thence (though, to be sure, no one was likely to hold him responsible for the eventual failure). It was an ominous sign that Republican candidates had just lost four of five by-elections. WFB: "There has, of course, been a lot of talk about Mr. Nixon as an albatross. Is it your judgment that if Mr. Nixon were to decide tonight that he wanted to become a poet or whatever, and eliminate himself without any sort of residual stigma, under such circumstances as those would you project that the party would have an easier time in November?" GB: "You are not going to like this answer because I know of your intellectual alacrity, but I am not going to get into these hypotheses because this is not going to happen. I know and respect the views of the very distinguished Senator from New York named Buckley ... My view is it is wrong for the President to resign, it is wrong for him to be forced out of office; the system has got to work, the system will work in fairness...." WFB: "You say it's like saying, 'What if the Pope became a Seventh-Day Adventist?'" GB: "Well, something like that. I wish I had thought of that, but, yes, I don't think it's in the makeup of the man."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.376
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00ANCWN50
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6310
  - "The Blackmailing of the President" Guests: Hunt, E. Howard (Everette Howard), 1918-2007.: Fine, Ralph Adam.: Bernstein, Nina.: Owen, John W., 10 May 1974 (Item Program Number S0135, 332)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 109: 3
    Program details: WFB begins by quoting John Dean's testimony to the Watergate committee: "'I told the President that Hunt wanted $72,000 for living expenses and $50,000 for attorneys' fees, and, if he did not get the money and get it quickly, he would have a lot of seamy things to say about what he had done for John Ehrlichman ...' " In Mr. Hunt's previous Firing Line appearance (s0077) the subject was the CIA and the Bay of Pigs; here he and his host explore the similarities and differences between official acts of clandestine agents and unofficial operations like the Plumbers'. Specifically, Mr. Hunt explains that the financial arrangement he had demanded was simply the clandestine services' traditional way of taking care of the families of captured agents. WFB: "I'm wondering what it is that caused [Nixon and his men] to use that term [blackmail], considering that you were saying this was really a traditional arrangement." EHH: "Well, I certainly understood it traditionally; obviously others did not, who should have."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.378
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6312
  - "Where Do We Go from Here in the Middle East?" Guests: Sayegh, Fayez A. (Fayez Abdullah), 1922-1980.: Orbach, William.: Greenberg, Lynn.: Almazani, Salah., 15 May 1974 (Item Program Number S0136, 333)
    Background File: Box/Folder 91: 10
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 109: 4
    Transcript: Box/Folder 171: 18
    Program details: Henry Kissinger's Shuttle Diplomacy was back in full swing, with, as WFB puts it, "apparently endless trips to Damascus, to Tel Aviv, to Cairo, to Cyprus." And there was "a vague sensation of movement: the Suez Canal is being reopened, the cease fire on the Egyptian front is months old." However, some observers believe that "nothing will happen until disposition is made of the demands of the Palestinian refugees," and Mr. Sayegh is of that camp. He might not convince any Israelis, but he makes his case in masterly fashion, working from UN Resolution 242, which sought to guarantee Israel's independence, back through the UN action of 1947 in establishing a " 'Jewish state'[which] made provisions for the protection of the Arabs who were to continue to live [there]," further back to the Balfour declaration, which "did not speak of a 'Jewish state'; it spoke of a 'national home,' " and back further still, to the centuries when, "Until Zionism came, it was perfectly normal for Jews and Arabs to live together in our part of the world. So I'm not presenting a vision that is against the nature of things. I am presenting a vision that would be a return to the nature of things once the aberrations of the last few decades are removed from the way."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.382
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00G707TCY
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6316
  - "Should the United States Disarm?" Guests: Aspin, Les., 10 May 1974 (Item Program Number S0137, 334)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 109: 5
    Program details: Rep. Aspin had been, as WFB reminds us, "one of Secretary McNamara's whiz kids in the Pentagon" (he would later himself briefly serve as Secretary of Defense under President Clinton), and he was now one of the Pentagon's sharpest critics. Host and guest agree that, as Rep Aspin puts it, "we should be buying the kind of weapons to counter the Soviet capabilities, not... just go ahead blindly and buy ships." Where the disagreement comes in--with lots of supporting detail on both sides--is over just how you tell what those needed weapons are. WFB: "Theoretically, if there were 200 million Russians and we had 200 million bullets, that would be all we would need if we could aim each bullet at each Russian." In the course of the hour we look at ships and planes and subs and cruise missiles and ICBMs, and Mr. Aspin's assertion, concerning the Soviet army, "Well, that's a very big army, but really half of it ... is on the Chinese border to prevent them waking up one morning and finding that the Chinese have chomped off a bit of territory."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.379
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00TZ8H1SW
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6313
  - "How Strong Should the Presidency Be?" Guests: McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-, 10 May 1974 (Item Program Number S0138, 335)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 109: 6
    Transcript: Box/Folder 171: 19
    Program details: "They are all giving thought nowadays," WFB begins, "to how the post-Watergate Presidency should look, how the office might be revised so as to bring it back within republican discipline." A rich discussion of how the Presidency reached its present state--which is, host and guest agree, too strong in some respects and too weak in others--enlivened by the off beat perspective that makes Mr. McCarthy arguably a better poet than he would have been a President: e.g., his proposal that instead of picking the President first and letting him pick his running mate, the "big fights at conventions ought to be over who's going to be the Vice President.... You pick the Vice President and you let him pick the presidential candidate. And you see all the good that would come out of that. You'd be picking a man who would say, 'I have no ambition at this point to be President. I'm going to take the least of all political jobs ... I will demonstrate my humility. And then I will be responsible for the man I pick to be President.' "
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.380
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6314
  - "Justice and the Fifth Amendment" Guests: Williams, Edward Bennett., 3 May 1974 (Item Program Number S0139, 336)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 109: 7
    Program details: Political violence had died down with the "Vietnamization" of the war, but ordinary crime had risen, and the courts increasingly seemed unable to cope. "One suggested remedy," as Mr. Buckley frames the question, "is a drastic new look at the Fifth Amendment and its interpretation by the Supreme Court, and here to say, 'Leave it alone,' is Edward Bennett Williams," whose clients had included Jimmy Hoffa and Frank Costello. A brilliant duel that takes the question far beyond the Warren Court--back to the beginnings of Anglo-American jurisprudence, and before that to the medieval Church and to the Talmud. "I think that in a free society it is essentially unfair and essentially unfree to confront one suspected of a crime with conviction if he confesses his guilt, perjury if he denies it, or contempt if he refuses to answer it. It seems to me it is essentially like saying to a small child who is suspected of taking your loose change ... 'If you admit it, you will be thrashed for stealing; if you deny it, you will be thrashed for lying; and if you refuse to answer, you will be punished for disobedience.'"
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.377
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6311
  - "Amnesty" Guests: Clark, Ramsey, 1927-, 3 June 1974 (Item Program Number S0140, 337)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 109: 8
    Transcript: Box/Folder 171: 20